Roger Watts

Tampa FL, 33624 • (813) 203-3296 • wattsr1@hotmail.com

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/roger-watts-30776289 GitHub: https://github.com/wattsr1

Professional Summary

Data specialist with extensive experience in research and management. Desire to apply strong analytical and communication skills to create a comprehensive understanding of the information available. Experience in developing databases and ensuring accuracy for inventory and key metrics for measuring success. Focused on using my diverse experience in research and education to focus on data analytics and visualization to forge a new career path. Experience in programing, data mining and statistical analysis with Python, R, SAS, and SQL along with data visualization using Tableau, JavaScript, and HTML.

Technical Skills

Tools: Python, JavaScript, HTML, Tableau, PowerBi, SAS, R, Excel, Word, VBA

Databases: SQL, MongoDB, Access

Projects

Mission to Mars web scraping | https://github.com/wattsr1/Mission-to-Mars.git

- Created app and website that scrapes news articles on developments for missions linked to the exploration of Mars
- Formulated code for the app and design of the webpage
- Project was created using Python and MongoDB with Flask app interacting with HTML template.

Weather Analysis Application | https://github.com/wattsr1/World_Weather_Analysis.git

- Analysis of global weather data gathered through an API to view optimum destinations for travelers based on weather data.
- Developed code and documentation for the project
- Mapped data using Python through Jupyter Notebook and incorporated Pandas modules for analysis

Ride Sharing Data Analysis | https://github.com/wattsr1/PyBer_Analysis.git

- Investigated data related to a dataset from a ride sharing company to determine trends present in the data
- Created the code and conducted the analysis and visualization of the data
- Interpreted the data using Python and Pandas modules for statistical data and visualizations

Professional Experience

NORTHERN NUTRIENTS - REGINA, CANADA

Research and Development Manager

Jan 2019 - Dec 2019

- Engineered and executed 3 research project analyzing plant performance with the use of newly developed seed treatment and fertilizers
- Formulated 2 reports presenting data at 2 tradeshows and 1 conference.

HAS UNIVERSITY OF APPLIED SCIENCE - DEN BOSCH, NL

Lecturer – International Food and Agribusiness

Aug 2015 – Aug 2018

- Restructured curriculum content on various topics related to the agriculture, research, and horticulture industry which increased student enrolment in crop production modules from 30% student enrollment to 45%
- Demonstrated active engagement in curriculum development resulting in

added responsibilities for the program in addition to required duties

- Chairman of the Examination Committee
- Curriculum Development Manager
- Executed a 'Train the Trainer' project for Indonesian agriculture trade schools which helped develop skills of 24 Indonesian instructors.
- Supervised 10 over 3 years student international supply chain management projects which resulted in 4 student placements within the companies they worked with.

HAPLOTECH - WINNIPEG, CANADA

Research and Development Manager

May 2014 – June 2015

- Controlled commercial research trials of newly developed canola and wheat hybrid crops for newly created collaborative breeding model
- Coordinated the experimental design, data collection, and analysis for varietal selection allowing project to increase from 3 trials in 1 region to 15 trials in 5 regions
- Developed R based analysis programs for rapid data analysis and visualization of experiment results reducing the time required for data analysis by 25%

DUPONT PIONEER - CARMAN, CANADA

Senior Research Associate

Apr 2011 - May 2014

- Facilitated a team of 5 full time employees and 3 seasonal employees
- Completed 3 years of commercial research projects for the development of new corn hybrid varieties with annual operational budget of \$750,000
- Integrated the agronomic and research support staff through active communication with senior research scientists resulting in an increase in productivity of 25%
- Enhanced inventory management and trial preparation protocols which reduced seeding errors to below 0.5% from 2%.

Education

CERTIFICATE OF DATA ANALYTICS: University of Central Florida

- Intensive program focused on developing technical programming skills
- · Excel, VBA, Python, R, JavaScript, SQL Databases, Tableau, Big Data, Machine Learning

MASTER'S DEGREE - PLANT BREEDING: UNIVERSITY OF MANITOBA • WINNIPEG, MB

- · Advanced statistics, research design and data analysis
- Genetic marker analysis of breeding population

BACHELOR'S DEGREE - PLANT BIOTECHNOLOGY: UNIVERSITY OF MANITOBA • WINNIPEG, MB

Plant biotechnology and physiology studies

DIPLOMA - CROP PRODUCTION: UNIVERSITY OF MANITOBA • WINNIPEG, MB

· Agronomics and Business Management in crop production

Professional Certifications and Training

Business Analysis Program	Cert #2546439	Simplilearn	May 2021
Certification Name	Cert #2503051	Simplilearn	Apr 2021
Agile Scrum Master	Cert #2384503	Simplilearn	Jan 2021
SQL Training	Cert #2272400	Simplilearn	Nov 2020